[Music]
hello everybody and welcome to the ask a
video show episode 120. i hope you're
all doing very well the way i am
and uh today as you know we discuss
science and technology so before we get
into it let's take a look at who all is
there with us and let me greet you all i
can see abhishek
uh
swapnil samarth kuldeep priyanshi
parikshit
pratham anonymous
vaibhav shashank um
and lots of other people ashima abeer
parikshit
trupti
kavith ombarek
uh nilesh patel swapnil everybody else
uh
nice to have you all with us tonight
and uh before we begin
i get this question lots of times as to
how do we uh how do how can you all ask
questions so that's the question i get
all the time uh so just let me explain
how you can ask me questions
uh what you need to do is in the
comments below uh you need to ask a
question and use the hashtag uh this is
the hashtag ask a widget you need to use
this hashtag because that's the way i'm
gonna find your questions i'm gonna
search for the hashtag and that's how
i'll find it if you don't use the
hashtag i may not be able to see your
question if you use the wrong spelling i
may not be able to see it so use the
hashtag ask your question keep it short
one or two sentences some people write
entire paragraphs i can't take those
questions it will take me a lot of time
to just read the question i want to
optimize the time that we have here at
our disposal
so keep your questions short and precise
one one sentence two sentences maybe
three at most make it fast and
so that's how you ask questions all
right
okay uh let us get into the questions as
always we have a bunch of questions and
let's get into it
so the first question is by mr swapnil
swapnamishra there are claims that there
is a new ocean forming in africa because
of an earthquake in the afar region in
which apparently expanded the east
african rift valley should we be calling
it a strait or a sea before calling it
an ocean
okay so uh apparently there are claims
that there's a new ocean forming in
africa inside africa because of an
earthquake in the afar region of our
region the afar region in africa is the
ethiopian region yeah north
uh east let's take a look at the map
that's the best way to understand what's
happening
do we have a map somewhere
we should have a map all right all right
maps okay let's take a look at the world
so this is
the map
and let's go to the afar region north
uh the horn of africa so this is the
region we're talking about all right
ethiopia
so let's take a look at the satellite
image do we see an ocean somewhere here
do we see an ocean do we see
a straight or whatever
we do have the indian ocean region here
somalia
and kenya tanzania etc we have the horn
of africa we have the gulf of aden we
have the red sea we have the strait of
baba al-mandib where is the ocean
that uh is apparently there where is the
new ocean that's forming where the west
was the straight as you can see there's
nothing
right
so
as we can see from the evidence that we
have at hand observational evidence
there is no such thing that's happening
there there have been earthquakes in
this region yes but uh no such thing is
happening there is no new ocean forming
now uh what's the deal with the rift
valley the east african rift let's take
a look at that what does that mean
so the rift valley let me put that on
the screen
so what is this rift valley it's it's
something that's apparently quite
consequential
to human history
so let's take a look at this the great
rift valley this doesn't give us a lot
of information so let's look here i need
a bigger image
so in this region we have the
great rift valley the east african rift
valley which apparently played a
significant role in human evolution
yeah so as you can see this region is
the rift valley
and
what does it actually look like this is
what it looks like
so and how does a rift valley form how
did this this rift valley form it formed
as a result of tectonic activity can you
see this
so you have tectonic activity which
which happens because of the in the
magma under the earth's surface you have
tectonic plates that keep moving all the
time it happens over geological time
scales millions of years tens of
millions of years hundreds of millions
of years and because of that you have
these continental plates that keep keep
moving some go under the other and
that's what happens right so this is a
process that takes millions tens of
millions hundreds of millions of years
and we can see this happening in slow
motion so even if there's an earthquake
even if there is some such
geological
uh
phenomenon that happens
it won't happen over a week's time or a
month's time or a year's time or a
decades time even a century time it's
going to happen over hundreds tens of
millions of years hundreds of millions
of years so the answer to this question
is yes there are earthquakes in this
region it's an it's a seismically active
reasonably seismically active region you
have these tectonic plates that are
pulling away from each other which is
causing the formation of a valley but
that's going to happen over millions of
years so if our descendants are around
let's say 10 million years from now they
may see a whole different geological
landscape in this region in east africa
maybe at that time there could be the
beginning of the formation of some kind
of
ocean or straight or something uh like
like the way the mediterranean sea
formed a long long long time ago that
sort of thing right so from the
observational evidence it is extremely
clear completely clear that there is no
such thing there is no new ocean that's
forming there if somebody makes the
claim you can verify it for yourself
if someone claims that so-and-so thing
is happening why don't you take a look
at the map and see is it happening
verify for yourself as you can see it's
not there it would happen perhaps
but not anytime soon right not in our
lifetimes not in a million years maybe
on time scales longer than that maybe an
order of magnitude
greater than that so that's where we are
as far as this is concerned
right next question
says how does photographic memory work
is it something people are born with or
can someone develop it later
so what is a photographic memory it's
apparently something in
it's it's something that a few people
have a very it's a rare
uh
phenomenon some people can memorize
things uh in extraordinary great detail
as if they have a photograph in front of
them
uh
so i think this is something that could
that is extremely uncommon if it even
does exist i don't have a photographic
memory i am a very forgetful person uh
i i tend to forget faces i tend to
forget names
uh
no disrespect i've met lots of people
and i next day i will not remember them
if you remember i we used to have this
video chat session
i did of a few video chat sessions ask a
budget right and i would have people
coming in and i had this rule that if
you have come
once in a video chat then for the next
month you cannot come and people kept on
coming and i could not remember their
faces because once i'm done i forget
that
so
uh so yeah i don't i clearly don't have
a photographic memory or anything like
that i remember remember certain things
very well things that i find very
interesting other things i don't really
pay attention so how does photographic
memory work uh first of all some people
are good at memorization naturally they
have a natural inclination
or aptitude for memorizing certain
things you can't memorize everything
some people are good at remembering
faces some people are good at
remembering
words or text some people are good at
remembering equations or whatever
and
people who
have this natural ability or a naturally
good memory they can be trained further
there are certain
organizations that may or may not exist
they're called intelligence agencies
we know of you cia fbi mossad raw and so
on
so they these organizations employ
what's known as
spies in the espionage business trade
craft and they obviously will recruit
people
who are good at this who are good at
memorizing things and then there are
certain techniques
that are taught to these
uh fledgling spies as to and which helps
them memorize vast amounts of
information and you know memorize it as
long as it is required and then they can
get rid of it from their memory
so some of these people may have
photographic memories
people photographic memories are alleged
to be a prevalent among top class like
one person of the one person kind of
poker players
gamblers etc they
are some of them are able to memorize
things and you know that that helps them
win whatever game they are playing poker
or whatever that's what i've heard
so it's something that is alleged to
exist some people may have it i'm sure
i'm sure
but uh and and some people may be born
with exceptional memories and you can
certainly develop it further so if you
have a good memory there are
memorization techniques that you can
learn
that would improve your memory so the
more you improve the more you practice
it the better your memory will become
so it's an acquired skill and it's also
something you're born with and that's
just how it works in most things in life
okay sanatori says how do birds fly how
do they take off so effortlessly hold
themselves in the air and have a safe
land landing is it magic how come they
don't need fuel
firing fuel creates a force to launch a
plane like how birds legs propel itself
for a takeoff does it mean any flying
machines need a fuel is it possible to
engineer an aircraft a plane without any
kind of fuel okay
how do birds fly it's a good question
so
we know we all see aircraft yes aircraft
taking off and landing and flying and
all that so there are two components
when it comes to aircraft there are
multiple components but let's keep it
very simple let's simplify it
oversimplify it for the sake of
understanding
an aircraft
has wings
that create lift that generate lift let
me explain in a moment what lift means
so they have wings that generate lift
and they have a propulsion system they
have jet engines or propellers or
whatever propellers pull the aircraft
forward and jet engines push the
aircraft forward that's how it works so
they have propulsion they have wings to
generate lift and they have stabilizers
like the tail stabilizer etcetera in
aircraft to keep it stable
so that's how aircraft work
so you need lift generation and you need
propulsion and you need something to
stabilize your flight in the case of
aircraft you have that in the case of
birds
the wings that they have come in
different sizes and shapes
let's take a look at what birds look
like just a second when you put birds
on the screen
um
where are we
here we are
so this is a different examples of birds
some are big some are small they come in
different sizes and shapes
some have large wings some have small
wings
and so on so that's what birds look like
the descendants of the avian dinosaurs
in the case of eagles they've got large
wings vultures have got large wings with
with a great wingspan sparrows
hummingbirds have short wings and so on
right
so in the case of birds they use their
wings for two purposes not just one
purpose
they use their wings
for propulsion
as well as for lift generation and force
and for stability so birds have tails
tails kind of act like stabilizers they
stabilize the flight
and the flapping of the wings
is what
gives them propulsion and once they are
airborne they use the wings for
lift generation also so what is lift
lift is this phenomenon in which the air
pressure below the wing surface is
higher than the air pressure above the
wing surface which results in an upward
force that pulls that pushes the bird up
upwards or the aircraft upwards that is
a simplified version a simplified
explanation of what lift is
so in aircraft you have wings the the
the
design of the wings is such that when
you push the aircraft forward using
propulsion this is going to be this lift
that is generated the air pressure on
top above the wing will be lower than
the air pressure below the wing which
pushes the aircraft upwards
and that's what
makes it fly
so in the case of birds it is the
flapping of the wings that provides the
propulsion upward propulsion as well as
backward forward propulsion and it
generates lift and it makes the birds
fly in the case of large birds with
great wingspans uh vultures
eagles condors albatrosses etc they've
got very wide and large wings
and once they're airborne they use
certain techniques to stay
up there afloat
while conserving energy so there is this
phenomenon called thermals air thermals
which are currents of air uh see
when the sun's
energy
uh falls on the earth it's incident on
the earth the surface of the earth is
unevenly heated
in certain parts of the of the earth's
surface you have forests which remain
cooler sometimes you have mountains and
hills which which
produce shadows that keeps certain parts
of the of the ground cooler than the
others so you have uneven distribution
of heat on the earth's surface and
because of that
you have the production of these
thermals which are circulating currents
of warm air that go upwards that push
upwards so in the case of eagles and
vultures they use these thermals
to just they just extend their winds out
their wings out and they
somehow sense these thermals and they
stay afloat on the thermals so they
conserve energy they don't have to flap
the wings and it's the upward movement
of this of this warm uh air
that keeps the birds flying for for very
long hours of amount of periods of time
hours
vultures can just uh
fly around
for hours while conserving a lot of
energy so that is typically how it
happens the bird's legs provide the
initial impetus the first jump and then
it's a flapping of the winds that
produces the
the uh
the
thrust
and
the lift both at the same time now the
other part of the question is does any
does it mean that in any flying machine
must need a fuel in the case of birds
well you don't put petrol or diesel or
jet fuel into birds but birds
do burn fuel in order to fly they have
to expend energy to produce the flapping
of the wings and all that where does it
come from from the food they eat
and there is the metabolism the the
the atp cycle adrenosine triphosphate
cycle that produces the energy
that powers the muscles that's the whole
thing that's the biology behind it so
yes birds do
use energy they use fuel
uh without fuel if you if you starve a
bird it won't fly it won't be able to
fly it will lose energy it will die yeah
so so in the case of uh biological
systems like birds humans etc we we have
this entire
atp cycle that produces energy in our
bodies
um
so
any flying machine needs some kind of
fuel is it possible to engineer an
aircraft without any kind of fuel you
have gliders
so in the case of gliders uh what's it
like what does a glider look like let me
show you what a glider looks like yes
let's take a look at sliders
one second let me share that once again
these are gliders these are various
kinds of gliders these aircraft glide
they don't have any any
any motor
they don't take any fuel
so this is a humor this is a person who
is gliding on this
this wing kind of design
this is the these are different kinds of
gliders right
so that's what it looks like so how do
these aircraft
work how do they fly they have to be
towed you have a single wing aircraft
for double wing aircraft double engine
aircraft or whatever that is that uh
that pulls this aircraft forward so you
need a cable
you need a cable and this uh the glider
is attached it is towed behind an
aircraft that has an engine that has
fuel and once that is airborne when it's
once it reaches a certain altitude the
cable is detached right and then the
pilot will use thermals just like
vultures and eagles in order to stay
afloat for a long period of time
eventually they will have to land
and that's how it works so that's how
gliders work the gliders do not have
fuel but they cannot stay afloat uh uh
stay in the air indefinitely
and uh
you can
engineer a plane that uses electrical
energy for instance you can engineer a
plane with very large wings that will
have solar panels it will be uh powered
by solar power but even in that case
there is a fuel which is light sunlight
right uh so you do need fuel for for
for a flight
in one way or the other you need it
so i hope that explains how all this
works
okay oj chaturvedi says you can't
actually terraform mars since it has no
magnetic fields and the core might just
be dead
too so even if you make another
atmosphere it will die out soon enough
well technically you are correct
conceptually you are right uh
the second part is right the first part
isn't right you can certainly tell us
for mars
if you have
the engineering and technological
know-how you can do it it is possible
it's not beyond the realms of science to
terraform a planet it would take a
thousand years possibly yeah it's a slow
process a long process you can't do it
overnight in in a couple of weeks time
it takes time it's a process that could
take centuries but it can be done
you can warm the planet you can have
flowing water again you could make the
atmosphere thicker you could uh have
mirrors
con mirrors that that orbit the planet
which which uh
ensure that there's more sunlight on
that is incident on the surface that
would warm up the planet or you could do
a whole bunch of other things that could
warm the planet make water flow again
and make the atmosphere thicker there's
a lot of stuff you can do right there
are lots of different techniques there's
a whole bouquet of of techniques the
whole toolkit of techniques that you
could use to possibly re-engineer
the atmosphere of mars and terraform it
and make it more earth-like or
completely earth-like that could happen
now the second part of the so so you can
actually do it it is possible yes
there are problems first of all mars
doesn't have a strong magnetic field
it's got a very weak magnetic field so
there's always the problem of cosmic
rays of solar radiation that will even
if you make the atmosphere thicker it
will eventually strip over the
atmosphere once again so mars had an
earth-like uh atmosphere
it was an earth-like planet about four
or so billion years before today
and over a period of about two or three
hundred million years the atmosphere was
tripped away because the magnetic field
uh disappeared the core of the planet
cooled down it's a much smaller planet
planet compared to the earth so the core
of the planet solidified there was no
more
uh circulation of liquid metal inside
which killed off the magnetic field once
the magnetic field died the solar wind
was able to to
impact
the the atmosphere directly which
ionized it and stripped away the atoms
and over a period of two or three
hundred million years the atmosphere
dissipated away the planet became a dry
barren wasteland right so that's why
it's like this today once upon a time
there was flowing water oceans and who
knows what else over there so let's say
we do the same thing again you make it a
warm planet again you thicken the
atmosphere over a period of let's say a
thousand years so let's say today is
2022 maybe in
302 to 80 they could have a fully
terraformed planet with a thick
earth-like atmosphere flowing water
vegetation and all that let's say we do
it
it still doesn't have a magnetic field
absolutely right so once again the same
process will get to work the solar wind
cosmic rays etc will bombard the planet
right
there is no magnetic field to shield
this thing the atmosphere so the solar
wind will start stripping over the
atmosphere
it will
again
die out the atmosphere will again be
stripped away but not soon enough like
it says like it says here it won't be
soon enough
it will take another
2 300
million years for that to happen
how long has the human species been
around how long has homo sapiens been
around
250 000 years 300 000 years a quarter of
a million years
we're talking about 100 200 300 million
years so as far as we are concerned
that is way far away in the future if
the planet again becomes barren for our
intents and purposes it's going to be
earth like forever for longer than the
human species has existed that is good
enough for us that is absolutely good
enough for us and that's why people want
to terraform mars there is talk of it we
still don't have the engineering uh
we still don't have the means to do it
the science is very clear it can it can
be done but we need to uh become
technologically more advanced in order
to be able to do that first of all we
have to reach there
so that's how it is
yes eventually the atmosphere will again
be stripped away over a period of
100 plus million years
which is essentially forever for us and
that's why it makes sense to do it if we
can all right hope this explains
the scenario
says
what is a dormant black hole recently a
team of astronomers have found the first
ever dormant black hole it's located in
the large magellanic cloud a satellite
galaxy of the milky way
see a black hole is a black hole
it may be
it may be active it may be dormant that
is all okay but black holes are black
holes black holes are very
it's actually quite simple what a black
hole is it's it's a region of space that
apparently contains a singularity a
region
of infinite curvature of space-time and
infinite density and that is shielded
from our eyes by an event horizon right
so we can't actually see it we can't we
can't ever see a naked singularity it's
always shielded by an event horizon so
that's what a black hole is it absorbs
it it gives off almost no light at all a
little bit yes hawking radiation and so
on that's what a black hole is now
what's the difference between an active
black hole and a dormant black hole an
active black hole isn't is a black hole
that is actively in the process of of
ingesting material
so it's visible so when material falls
into a black hole yeah
it goes
it forms what's called an accretion disk
which is a disc
uh a circular disc in which the material
slowly falls into the black hole it's
accelerated to greater and greater
velocities it glows it emits some
radiation
in various wavelengths radio wave
radio waves uh visible light
um and much more right so it's visible
and that's how we actually detect black
holes because their effects are visible
you can see that it's in the process of
absorbing swallowing maybe eating a star
or eating a cloud of gas and that is
heated up and it's
that's how the black holes
location can be determined because of
these telltale
signs of its existence what is a dormant
black hole a black hole that's minding
its own business sitting alone somewhere
it's not actively eating anything and
that's why it's completely invisible the
truth is black holes are not black they
are transparent they do have this this
they do distort space time so if you can
look for if you look for micro lensing
events you know gravitational lensing in
which space
in which objects behind the black hole
are distorted by its gravitational uh
effects
then you can detect such a black hole
and recently it seems
astronomers have been able to detect
such a black hole so just a black hole
mining its own business not eating
anything completely invisible but
suddenly they were able to detect the
distortion of some objects behind it and
that's why that's how they were able to
detect that's why that's how they were
able to determine that a black hole is
there a quiet
quiescent dormant black hole not doing
anything not active at all just sitting
there minding its own business right so
that is a dormant black hole a black
hole that is dormant is a black hole
that is not in the process of
swallowing matter whether it's a star
whether it's a whether it is a cloud of
gas or anything else dust whatever
that's a dormant black hole there could
be a dormant black hole in the milky way
in orbit around the sun we would never
know it of course we could indirectly
detect it because of its gravitational
effects yeah
and that is possibly what could be
planet nine or planet x x or whatever
they want to call it there seems to be
an unknown object in the far reaches of
the solar system and its gravitational
pull is affecting the objects
in that region beyond the in the
trans-neptunian objects and beyond in a
certain way the plane of the orbit the
planes of the orbits of these objects
are tilted in a certain way which is
kind of an indicator that some massive
object is lurking out there in the dark
depths of the outer solar system now
it's possible it could be just a large
super earth-like planet or it could be
an ancient primordial black hole that's
just sitting there no one can see it but
it's
you know shepherding the uh
solar system objects in that region in a
certain manner right so that is what we
mean by a dormant black hole a black
hole that is invisible it's minding in
its own business it's not eating
anything actively completely invisible
there could be so many such black holes
out there
and we will most likely never detect
them because they
because they're black they're dark
they're transparent
and unless we have extremely sensitive
micro lensing detectors we won't be able
to detect them so recently it looks like
we have
done the first detection of one like you
say
in the large magellanic cloud it's great
so
so that's what it is
abhishek says are black holes like solid
balls
solid balls what's in between the event
horizon and the singularity of the black
holes what does it mean that the whole
mass is concentrated at the singularity
is it physically possible or is it just
a mathematical outcome excellent
question you ask these questions to your
physics professor they'll say shut up
look at the equations but this is how
you develop the understanding the
curiosity the conceptual foundation of
what black holes actually are
so as far as general relativity is
concerned a black hole is
as well for let's consider the simplest
case this for the schwarzschild black
hole a
non-rotating
black hole with no charge
so in that case it's just a sphere
the event horizon is a spherical region
yeah and within the event horizon at the
very center is this
monstrous entity a singularity
it's a monster it is a region of
infinite density and infinite curvature
it's infinity it's an infinitive how do
you define an infinity mathematically
you take a number and you divide it by
zero
that's how you create an infinity
mathematically right and infinities are
unphysical they make no sense whatsoever
so an infinity is an indication that
your equations have broken down and
there's a division by zero happening in
your equations which means that at some
region in space your equations don't
work that's what it means
so the equations of general relativity
break down
at the quantum level at the ultra
microscopic subatomic level that's where
general relativity no longer works it
works brilliantly on large scales
on macroscopic scales but it simply
doesn't work
at the quantum scale so the the fact
that it gives us a singularity indicates
that the equations don't quite work
there is some defect in the equations
and we have not been able to incorporate
the quantum world
the quantum domain into general
relativity and that's the search that
everyone
is making the search for quantum gravity
a quantum theory of gravity right that's
what everyone's looking for so
so we don't quite know what's inside the
event horizon
clear i i don't believe that there's a
singularity out there there's something
else going on inside the black hole but
there is no way for us to know because
the event horizon is opaque uh there is
uh
this thermal radiation that that is
emitted depending on the temperature of
a black hole a black hole has certain
properties mass charge
temperature entropy all that yeah
angular momentum the three basic
properties of a black hole are mass
charge and angular momentum a black hole
also has a temperature which means it's
its thermodynamic system and if you have
a temperature you also have entropy
which is the measure of disorder or the
measure number of possible microstates
that a black hole can have it's
proportional to the surface area of a
black hole so that's what it is inside
we don't know what is there there could
be a bunch of strings there could be a
bunch of photons inside a black hole you
can perfectly well model
a black hole as a bunch of photos as a
photon gas
or or something else you could there's
there's plenty of mathematical toy
models of black holes you can create a
bunch of fuzz balls a bunch of strings a
bunch of photons a bunch of gravitons in
a bag you know
that sort of thing so we don't quite
know is it solid not quite solid the
event horizon actually may not mean
anything you may go through an event the
event horizon and inside you may still
find empty space it's quite possible
and
one of the ways of looking at a black
hole is a fluid is a fluid
there is this whole field called magneto
hydrodynamics of black holes
so which is
what is magneto hydrodynamics it is the
study of magnetized fluids
so a black hole can be
modeled as a fluid
yeah even that's possible
so there are different approaches
that we can use in order to understand
what black holes are like or or maybe to
try and probe
what black holes could be
as of today until we find a proper
working theory of quantum gravity a
quantized theory of gravity we will not
quite know no
but yeah so so that's what a black hole
is there are possible answers that i can
give nobody has the absolute correct
answer because no first of all we don't
have a black hole in a lab sitting
somewhere that we can go and observe and
test and you know probe and prod we
don't have it
uh
we see certain objects that appear to be
black holes we have one
monster black hole sitting at the center
of our own galaxy
yeah we have other black holes i mean
most large galaxies seem to have black
holes at their center
and so yeah we also have the first ever
detection of a black hole which is
cygnus
cygnus 61 or something which happened in
the 1960s 70s they're about here
so yeah so so that's the thing
we don't have black holes to play with
we don't have black holes in a lab that
we could test and that's why we are
unable to actually
uh
test it experimentally
so that in short is what i can offer you
and research is in progress and
hopefully someday we will make a
breakthrough hopefully hopefully in this
century the 21st century i hope is the
century of gravitation when we actually
figure out what gravity actually is
so far we have made zero progress in the
past 22 years of the 21st century how
when how long has it been 21 years
thereabouts yeah
so yeah that's the answer
okay so home says what are fields
magnetic fields gravitational fields etc
are they just some quantum particles
that flow
uh is it some form of energy and why do
they follow certain patterns
how are electric and magnetic fields
interrelated with each other okay
uh
let's talk about the first part of the
question what are fields
so as you know i'm inside a room it's a
three-dimensional room yes it's got a
height height it's got a length it's got
a breadth three dimensions x y and z x's
right
so you could create a coordinate system
inside this room one centimeter notches
it's a three dimensional coordinate
space and at each point
in this coordinate system
there is a certain temperature in this
room
right so you could for each point
in coordinate system in this room you
could assign a number which represents
the temperature at that very point in
space so that is
a field
yeah a coordinate system
three-dimensional coding
coordinate system in which each of the
coordinate points has a certain value
in the case of temperature it's a scalar
it's just a temperature it's just a
number it's a magnitude which represents
the temperature in celsius or whatever
you want or kelvin yeah so that is the
temperature field in this room it's a
changing field it changes with time
let's say we want to talk about uh
atmospheric pressure
so once again at each point in this
coordinate system in this room there is
a certain
atmospheric pressure which changes it
may not be the same over here compared
to here or up here or down there right
it changes so that is the the field of
atmospheric pressure
now
so these are just numbers only
magnitudes now so that's a scalar field
a scalar field is a field which has
numbers only magnitudes and nothing else
these magnitudes may represent physical
quantities like temperature pressure
whatever right
in the same room that i am in
at every point in this
three dimensional space
the atmosphere the air over here has a
certain velocity
in meters per second
let's say over here it is the air is
going in that direction
at one meter per second over here the
air is going in this direction at 1.3
meters per second so at every point
inside this room the air has a certain
velocity not just the speed
in meters per second but also a
direction
so this is a vector field because it has
magnitude and direction
right
and then you have tensor fields which i
will not go into they have spinner
fields and so on so that is what a field
is it's essentially just a coordinate
system in which each coordinate has a
certain quantity it could be a scalar
quantity just a number or a vector
quantity or a tensor quantity and so on
so you have magnetic fields
gravitational fields and all that and in
in quantum field theory you have
well each of the fundamental particles
has its own field
which permeates all of space time it's
an infinite field if the infinite if the
universe is infinite
so there is a for there's a proton field
i have protons in my body in my shirt in
in this instrument over here
and
these protons are part of a proton field
that
permeates the entire universe the
protons have quarks there is a quark
field there are there are different
kinds of chords and each of these
different kinds of quarks has its own
field now
in the case of qft quantum field theory
the universe is made of fields and the
actual
universe that we experience is an
illusion
everything is just fields
and particles like protons or neutrons
or electrons or whatever all these
particles fundamental particles
are excitations local excitations in
fields
so if if there's a proton here it means
that there is a
spike
a spike in the field it's a local
excitation of the infinite
proton field and so on
so that is qft quantum field theory and
there's a whole lot behind that so that
in brief is what fields are so i am
inside this field
this room is a field there's atmospheric
pressure field temperature field uh air
velocity field and that is not just in
this room it's everywhere on the planet
and so on
and now the other question is so so that
is what fields are right there are
different kinds of fields in qft there
are at least 17 feet there are 17 fields
this is the gravitational field which is
not part of the of of the standard model
and so on now how are the electric and
magnetic fields interrelated with each
other
their relation is very simple look at
the maxwell field equations
the maxwell equations tell you how the
electric and magnetic fields are related
to related to each other electricity and
magnetism are two sides of the same coin
electromagnetism electricity can
generate magnetic fields and magnetic
fields can generate electricity yeah so
if you want to understand how they are
related to each other how they are
intertwined you have to study the
maxwell um the maxwell field equations
google it and
so i will not go into detail in that but
overall i i hope you understand
conceptually what fields are
okay kabir singh says in your previous
episodes
you have explained
about gene editing technology crispr
some countries like us china etc may
have secret and some secret groups may
be using this the purpose could be
anything making super human super
soldiers super foods and so on
it's suggested
to avoid going against nature
so what do you think could be the
consequences of genetic modification in
the long run
yeah that's that's a big question so
let's say you are trying to secretly
genetically modify human beings and
create
designer babies or whatever
so what is a designer baby there is a
very real possibility in the
the short-term future that rich people
could be able to have designer babies
which means that you look at the genome
of the baby you're gonna have and you do
some editing you insert certain genes
that are maybe uh
are
that they code for certain kinds of
traits physical traits
some abilities maybe the child will be
like 20 iq points more intelligent than
a regular child or maybe instead of five
feet eight inches tall the child will
grow to six feet two inches tall or
maybe the child will have fast twitch
muscle fibers or more athletic or a
certain eye color certain skin color
certain hair color
or certain other traits so it could very
soon become possible to do that
yeah so that's what we call designer
babies so that could create a race of
superhumans that only the rich people
can afford and that would even widen
even further the gap between the rich
and the poor the poor will not have
access to such technologies the rich
will have it and over over multiple
generations the rich will become
superhumans and the poor will become
the whatever is left of humanity
that is uh a dystopian possibility that
could be out there in the future that
could actually happen yeah that that's
possible
uh so that is what crispr could do
obviously uh
uh
editing the human genome is frowned upon
it is called it is considered to be
medically it's called it's considered to
be unethical
human experimentation is unethical but
it is certainly possible that certain
countries certain groups could be doing
it
uh we know very well what kind of
history the cia has had project mk ultra
in which they did all kinds of terrible
things of their own citizens their own
people uh
nazi germany did certain terrible things
the uh
uh
imperial japan during the world war two
era did human experimentation i i hear
that the chinese
government has certainly as kind of
lacks standards when it comes to human
experimentation and they could be
producing designer babies
i
remember possibly reading somewhere that
a couple of twins were born in china
with edited genes
crispr edited genes and so on and
they're they're definitely doing this on
monkeys and other species
so yeah
this could very well will be the future
it's not a good future but that's just
how it is right it's not in our control
if if you have the technology if you
have the know-how if you have the money
then you could get it done you could
have such things done
uh so what are the consequences of doing
this well the consequences we may not
quite know what they are the human
genome is immense
i think it has more than 3 billion base
pairs
if i if i remember correctly it's very
complex
and we understand less than
less than five percent of the genome
yeah
uh only three to five percent of the
genome seems to code for proteins and
seems to make sense the rest of the
genome almost 95 of the genome all this
genetic information we don't understand
what it is it seems to do nothing
and yet it can't be the case that it
does nothing nature is parsimonious
evolution
does evolution is such that it doesn't
you will not have genes that that are
not useful it will the the evolutionary
process over millions of years get rid
of whatever is not gets rid of whatever
is not needed whatever is not useful
yeah
so if
the human genome has evolved such that
it contains so many genes so many base
pairs and all that then i am sure that
these base pairs these genes
have some purpose maybe it's a purpose
we don't quite understand yet
but they will have some purpose and we
don't know what is the effect what are
the consequences of editing a certain
part of the genome does it have
long-term downstream consequences on
other parts of the genome
does editing a certain
portion of the genome
eventually end up
affecting other parts of the genome and
having consequences we don't understand
it's quite possible
it is quite possible there are all these
scientists who say
that it's it's great to have gmos
genetically modified organisms
well we don't know the consequences of
what what what the downstream
consequences
10 generations down the line 20
generations on the line and how is it
going to affect the environment in the
ecosystem because no species no organism
exists in a vacuum in isolation
the entire ecosystem of the world of the
planet is interrelated
yeah it's dependent on all these
different species and if something
changes it's going to have consequences
on other species and other parts of the
ecosystem as well
so i think it's very dangerous
to start thinking that we can play god
it could have
massive
massively dangerous downstream
consequences 10 20 30 50 generations
down the line that's when the effects
could start becoming visible and by the
time it could be
impossible to reverse that because that
spread to so many uh individuals right
by the time
so i think it could be something
that's very dangerous it could end up
causing all kinds of defects in the
species
so one has to be very careful and i
think there's a good reason why human
experimentation is considered to be
unethical and it is like essentially
prohibited or and banned in most
civilized nations
so yeah
that's what it is
okay highly says cardiovascular disease
and cardiomyopathies seem to be the
number one cause of the of death well
it's it's a major cause of illness and
death for sure
uh the question is how far are we from
creating a cheap and flawless mechanical
heart that can permanently replace a
person's heart or 3d print the entire
heart do you think that it will happen
in this decade or so
well that's been the so-called holy
grail of
one of the holy grails of
medicine
to create an artificial heart that can
permanently replace
a deceased human heart so we have all
these lifestyle diseases you have
congestive heart failure you have
cardiovascular illnesses
cardiomyopathies and all caused by
who knows what yeah we'll not go there
so we have these problems right
uh
hearts that don't work well the hearts
that are failing and typically you would
need a heart transplant a full organ
transplant and hearts organs are
extremely scarce
i mean
for somebody to donate their heart they
would have to die
right so typically that's done in
in individuals who are who are either
in a vegetative state brain dead
completely blended proven
or someone who has met with an accident
but the organs are intact and if you can
harvest them quickly and if the
family allows that to happen then you
may have an organ so
for four transplants so that is uh
that's why there is a
massive scarcity
of
available organs and there's a huge
waiting list yeah
uh so that's why it's it it makes sense
to
try and develop
alternatives to human organ transplants
so one of the uh alternatives that
people are exploring is a zeno
transplantation that is that's something
i've spoken about a few episodes back uh
recently this year itself 2022 in
january i believe
a genetically modified pig heart was
transplanted into a human being into a
man and that person stayed alive was
able to live for a few months
eventually the person died because of
certain viruses
cytomegalovirus i believe it's called
porcine cytomegalovirus which was
present in the in the organ so the
company that provided the pig organ the
pig heart messed up and that's why the
person died but
until that happened the person was doing
well
so if you can genetically modify a pig
organ
and
then you could possibly trick the human
immune system into believing that it's a
human organ and you could make it work
perhaps yeah
or you could
try and engineer completely artificial
art people have been trying that for
decades
various
models of artificial hearts have been
created usually these are stop gap
arrangements until a person can receive
an actual transplant organ a human organ
right
so the human heart
is an incredibly complex
piece of biomechanical engineering it
has how many chambers i think four
chambers
it has ventricles it has connections to
the vena cava the aorta
and
it's it's quite complex
and it's it's something that is supposed
to stay with you for a century yeah if
you can live a century
uh so it's it's an it's a very complex
piece of engineering and people have
tried to replicate that
but thus far it's not been possible
and uh
i remember in the 1980s 1990s when i was
a kid people had tried creating these
plastic hearts with motors inside that
would help the blood flow and all that
so one of the problems is
how to power an artificial heart an
artificial heart needs to replicate the
functioning the beating or the pumping
functionality of the human heart
so for that to happen it has to be
powered you need some kind of engine
some kind of motor
you need some power source you could
have a heart with a battery
inserted in it or that's part of it
battery pack but then a battery can only
last so long
you would either need to recharge that
battery or need to replace it
now when you in when you open up a
person's chest
crack the sternum open open up the chest
remove the heart put something else in
its place
it's an incredibly traumatic event yeah
you the person will be sedated
anesthetized and the person will will
feel no pain or whatever will not be
conscious but it is incredibly traumatic
for the body
you know opening the opening of the
chest the thoracic cavity and tracking
the sternum and messing around with the
organs so it's not something you can do
every six months
it's not something you can do every two
years
ideally
you should not open up a person's
any part of the body not more than once
in 10 years
so ideally you want
a replacement artificial heart to be
able to last at least 10 years
without having to be you know serviced
or or replaced so that is still far away
in the future there are all kinds of
issues
um even artificial organs can face
rejection from the body the immune
system of the body is very powerful it
can degrade the functioning of the organ
and of course there's the problem of the
power source the battery do we have
opening in the in the chest with with
wires coming out and you attach a
battery there that's incredibly
inconvenient isn't it
so major
issues remain major challenges remain
but it's certainly something that
scientists want to achieve
so what's my prediction will this happen
in this decade most likely not
if it happens great but
there could be other more viable
alternatives like xenotransplantation if
you can
if you can artificially create big
organs big hearts you know artificially
grow them
or
grow pigs and then slaughter them
butcher them and get the heart out
that's another way that people do so if
you could do that and you could
genetically modify
the organ such that the
possibility of or or probability of
rejection immune rejection is low
and if you could
solve the problem of the porcine viruses
that could infect the human body
or or degrade the performance of the
organ
that could be a better option compared
to an artificial heart
so there are multiple approaches being
being explored right now
and maybe the xeno transplantation angle
may be more promising than a completely
artificial heart but even that is
something that i'm sure people are
pursuing so that is the scenario
as of today
okay riddhi says why is the plank
constant h so important even though its
value is so incredibly tiny 10 raised to
minus 34 that's the order of of its
magnitude why can't this be neglecting
for calculating the energy or any other
equation
uh so it's like this
what is this thing this planck constant
what is it
so
in quantum physics we
this has been experimentally proven
right
what has been experimentally proven
the the planck relation is that
the energy
of a let's say a photon
is proportional the energy of a photon
is proportional to its frequency or its
wavelength and what is the relation let
me put that on the screen
one second do we have it somewhere let
me um
let me put the plank relation on the
screen so that you
can understand what it is
all right here we are
so this is the blank relation e equals h
nu or let me give you a better
understanding of that
um
you can call it new you can call it
f or whatever so this is the planck con
the planck relation do we have a okay
here we are i hope this is visible
enough
so the energy so we have these this
equation here
what is e e is the energy of a photon
it is equal to h which is a constant
multiplied by nu which is the frequency
of that photon
which is equal to hc upon lambda c is
the speed of light and lambda is the
wavelength frequency and wavelength are
that's the relation right
so
there is a constant of proportionality
in here which is called which is denoted
by h which is the planck constant
and we have determined that its value is
of the order of 10 raised to minus 34
whatever units units it is
so this is something that just is there
you can't neglect it
i know it's so small
it's incredibly small 10 raised to minus
34 that's the kind of order of magnitude
it has
but that is how small the quantum world
is
and to make sense of the quantum world
too
we need this this is one of the most
fundamental and integral
parts of quantum mechanics without this
quantum mechanics it simply doesn't work
and it's not that something some
scientists have decided that we're going
to make it like this no this is what
nature tells us this is experimentally
proven again and again and again so
there is a constant of proportionality
which we call the planck concern you can
call it whatever you want but its value
is of the order of 10 raised to minus 34
whatever units it is you can look it up
right
so that is why it is so fundamentally
important because this is
how
this is the relation between the energy
of a photon and its wavelength and its
frequency so that is the the fundamental
importance of the planck constant
in quantum mechanics in in in quantum
physics and you simply can't neglect it
without this relation you can't
calculate the energy of the photon
that's the relationship between the
energy and the wavelength
this is where quantum mechanics begins
right it's max planck who
discovered this so to say at the at the
end of the 19th century i believe or the
very beginning of the 20th century i
don't remember the dates if you want if
you're interested you can look at look
that up but around around 1900 plus or
minus a few years to three years maybe
he discovered this and that was the
actual birth the beginning of quantum
mechanics and that is has is what has
transformed the world forever
so without quantum mechanics we would
have none of the technology that we
enjoy today we would not be having this
conversation right now yeah
so yeah so that's why the planck
constant is so important
aditya says
what is time what is the smallest unit
of time
how do we even say that the universe had
a beginning at t equals zero if we can
never stop dividing time into smaller
and smaller units
well it's like this we
there is a certain minimum unit of time
which makes sense and be below that you
the smaller units of time don't make
sense why is it so
so there is something called the planck
units we just spoke about the planck
constant yes h and all that so let's
take a look at what planck
units are
and instead of me writing it up i can
just put the wikipedia page on the
screen
so as always wikipedia is not entirely
reliable but in the case of science it's
more or less reliable
so there is something called planck
units
so these are different units of
measurement we have uh what are they
made of they're made up of the speed of
light in vacuum which is c the
gravitational constant g
the reduced planck constant h cross h
bar which is h planck constant divided
by 2 pi
and the boltzmann constant kb
using these four fundamental universal
constants you can create the planck
units
so these are the planck units the planck
length the planck mass the planck time
and the planck temperature the planck
temperature some people call it absolute
hot which is the highest temperature
that the universe could ever have
so the planck length can be calculated
as in as you can see in terms of these
fundamental constant constants and its
value is of the order of 10 raised to
minus 35 meters which is the so this is
the smallest length that makes any sense
physical sense in the universe the
planck length it's of the order of 10 is
to minus 35 meters the planck mass is
the minimum amount of mass that makes
sense in the universe it's of the order
of 10 to minus 8 kg apparently it looks
like yep
and the planck time
is the smallest unit of time that makes
sense in the universe which is of the
order of 10 raised to minus 44 seconds
so below that it time doesn't make sense
from whatever physics we know whatever
we know physics and whatever we know of
the universe so that is the
smallest
possible
unit of time that we can understand or
conceive of
using the physics
and the knowledge of physics and the
knowledge of the universe that we have
at our disposal right
so that is the smallest unit of time the
planck time or you could call it the
planck second if you want it's of the
order of 10 raised to minus 44 seconds
then it's minus 43 44 seconds the exact
amount
amount is given over here
so that is what it is right
so why do we say that the universe at
the beginning at t equal to 0 because
that's what observational evidence tells
us we know that the universe is
expanding
so if the universe is expanding it's
going to be expanding further in the
future you could interpolate back
interpolate the same process back in
time so if you if you reverse the
process of time you could see that the
universe was contracting contracting
contracting which means that it started
most likely at a point now if it started
as a single point a supposed singularity
then it would be a singularity of which
would have infinite density infinite
temperature it would be pure energy the
universe would have been pure energy at
the time
and the expansion of the universe would
have had a certain afterglow
yeah and we have detected that after
glow so observational evidence tells us
that this process which we call the big
bang actually happened all the
observational evidence tells us that it
actually happened
the radiation that's left over from the
big bang the after glow of the big bang
the cosmic microwave background edition
it's been detected it's out there it's
got a temperature of 2.5 2.7 or so
kelvin look at what the actual amount is
the actual value is
so all the x ex
observational evidence that we have at
our disposal tells us
that the universe had a beginning
and at some point in time most likely it
was concentrated
into a single point
that's the best
theory
the best model of the evolution of the
universe that we have the so-called big
bang theory
so that's why we say that the universe
at the beginning and
when the universe began time would have
been zero because time flowed after that
initial expansion of the universe so
that is why
we say that the universe at the
beginning at time t equal to zero and
like i showed the smallest unit of time
that we can think of we can construct
out of the theories of physics
is uh the planck time
of the order of 10 is to minus 44
seconds all right
okay next question
vishal says
what are your thoughts about vedic
rashmi theory by acharya agni vrataji
he has explained time space singularity
uh but in theory not mathematically
what do you think is it a possibility of
truth or just
trash
vedic rashmi theory i get lots of
questions about this vedic rashmi theory
so i tried to look it up
i tried to look up online what is this
vedic theory typically when you have a
theory of physics of nature of science
you would have papers
yeah a paper in which all the or the
fundamentals of the theory are laid out
properly and all that so i am able to
find nothing there is a book that's
available on amazon which costs
in india 10 000 rupees
ten thousand rupees are kidding me
and there is no literature available
online any any published paper
even a non-published paper a pre-print
even that is not available so i don't
know what this theory is some people
lots of people claim that it explains
everything time space universe all that
my question see what is a theory
any theory must
first of all
explain the universe as it is
it should explain everything that we
already know and then it should make
some improvements on what
we know it should make some predictions
so my question about the vedic rashmi
theory or whatever it's called is
does it explain the universe as you know
it what are the
fundamental presuppositions of this
theory what
what is a theory made up of made up of
what are the fundamental
uh concepts of this theory
what are the foundations of the theory
does this theory explain let's say the
four forces of nature does it explain
the strong nuclear force does it explain
the weak nuclear force does it explain
the electromagnetic force does it
explain the force of gravitation does it
explain uh maxwell's equations for
electromagnetics does it reproduce those
equations
does it does it explain special
relativity general relativity does it
explain the relative the relativistic
effects that a gps satellite must
account for has to adjust for
can it explain the perihelion precession
of mercury the planet
does it do that does it explain quantum
mechanics does it explain the quantum
tunneling involved in a transistor in
semiconductors can it explain fields
quantum field theory
can it explain population inversion the
principles behind lasers
does can it explain why the moon has
phases why does the planet venus have
phases why why is the moon tidally
locked with the earth
can it
explain any of these things
does it have mathematics built into it
what is the theory about is there any
other specific result
that
it
explains
in a testable result that it explains
does it explain various kinds of
observational evidence that we have
observational empirical evidence does it
predict anything new
if any of these things are correct if it
does any of these things why is the
information not available
in the public domain
so this is how you do science
you don't do science be on the basis of
faith on the basis of emotions
science is hard
science is very rigorous
so i have seen absolutely no evidence of
first of all what this vedic rashmi
theory is
what is the math behind it i mean you
have to construct a theory using math
not using words and where hand hand
waving
so so far i've tried to search for it
because people keep asking me this
question i have found absolutely no
information about this theory there is a
book available for 10 000 rupees are you
kidding me 10 000 rupees
so that's how it is so as far as i know
i i mean i know nothing about this
theory
i have found
no information about this theory in the
public domain
and i have seen some pdfs here and there
but it's all words there are no
equations in there if there are no
equations it's not math it's not it's
not science it's not physics
so that is all i can say about this
theory
if somebody can
if somebody has more information please
feel free to put it in the comments and
i will look it up but i
am good at finding information and i've
found no information
and i'm not going to spend 10 000 rupees
to buy a book and i don't know what
what's in there so
that's where we are
okay so not says i am fascinated about
inter interstellar space
we have two probes in interstellar space
voyager the voyager missions voyager 1
and voyager 2.
why don't we pursue more such missions
and what lies beyond our solar system so
what lies beyond our solar system we can
see what lies beyond resources beyond
resource system
we have astronomical evidence
of what is beyond the solar system the
nearest star is proxima centauri
um
we have lots of other stars in our
regional neighborhood tao sitai
uh epsilon eridani and lots of other
stars we have the entire milky way
galaxy that we are part of
we have our neighboring galaxy we have a
couple of satellite galaxies around the
milky way the
large and small magellanic clouds
the closest other
major galaxy is the andromeda galaxy
which is actually coming closer to earth
coming closer to our galaxy it's going
to merge
with our galaxy in
two and a half or so billion years yeah
i think
and then we have the local
supercluster the launcher or something
it's called supercluster and so on and
we can see far away galaxies and far
away things so we know what's outside
the solar system we know
we have the observational evidence we
have lots of it we have the hubble
space telescopes evidence we have the
new telescope out there the
james webb space telescope that is going
to throw new light on things so we know
what is out there we know what lies
beyond of course it's always great to
send probes
into interstellar space so that we
understand the environment that's at the
edge at the edges of the solar system
the bow shock and the radiation
environment temperature out there and
other things it's always good to have
that so the voyager probes and the
pioneer probes have given us some kind
of data so the pioneer probes there were
two pioneer uh
spacecraft that were launched in the
1970s i think in 1970 to 1973 pioneer 10
pioneer 11.
so these had certain purposes to to
actually examine various parts of the
solar system and send back photographic
evidence from close close by
so these two probes were launched in the
1970s early 70s
and
radio communications were lost with
these probes in the 1990s or in the
early 2000s yeah
uh then we had the two voyager
spacecraft voyager 1 and voyager 2 which
were launched in 1977
yeah and the purpose of these two
spacecraft was to give us photographic
evidence of the
gas giant planets jupiter saturn uranus
neptune
and eventually these two spacecraft have
entered interstellar space
more or less
so these are the two
and i believe even the pioneer
spacecraft are in now in interstellar
space
uh the voyager spacecraft are still
communicating with earth but i believe
that by 2025 communications will cease
because the
uh
because the power generating system will
fail
it will no longer be able to supply
sufficient power for the communications
to continue
so yes we have a few space probes out
there now uh why don't we do more of
that
why don't we pursue more such versions
because
it's it's first of all very expensive
space launches are expensive and uh it
takes a lot of time for us for a
spacecraft to reach
the edges of the solar system and
interstellar space so uh the voyager
spacecraft were launched in the 1970s
1977 yes
and i think it took at least 30 or 40
years for them
between 30 and 40 years for them to
reach the edges of the solar system it's
a very large
time
period it's a very long investment right
here to do
so uh and right now we have another
spacecraft it's called new horizons the
one that did the
flyby of pluto and
sent back the first proper images of the
of the dwarf planet
so even new horizons is eventually going
to enter into stellar space and as of
today there are no other spacecraft that
are doing that
so that is what's happening uh
in the future there could be another uh
another
project
called breakthrough star shot the
technology isn't quite there yet maybe
we could have it in in the next 10 20
years
so this breakthrough star shot project
will send a free will send
a fleet
of more than a thousand
micro spacecraft
into interstellar space and within 30 to
40 years they will reach our closest
nearing star proxima centauri
so these will these spacecraft will use
light sail technology and pulsed arrays
of lasers and all so that will happen
maybe in the next 10 20 years
so we have such missions
that could happen in the future but our
main objective right now is the moon and
mars because of commercial and other
reasons geopolitical reasons as well so
that's wha what's going on eventually if
humanity does well we could have
interstellar missions as well in the
future in the far future
okay naman sony says does isro hire
astrophysicists and astronomers what is
the scope for these fields in the
upcoming decades in india i want to
pursue this field i'm currently a ge
aspirant
okay what is israel israel stands for
indian space
research organization the name is very
misleading it doesn't do research in
space
the primary purpose of isro is to
develop
design and develop space launch
technologies which isn't which means
rockets
right so this the
the agency has developed uh a family of
rockets the pslv the polar space launch
vehicle the various gslv
variants geostationary space launch
vehicle and in the future we may have
more powerful rockets hopefully
reusable rockets and all that
the other
uh
agenda that isro has is to develop
various kinds of
satellites
so the primary purpose of isro is to
design and develop rockets
and satellites
so isro hires
uh it it could conceivably hire people
with a background or degrees in
astrophysics or astronomy
but they would be doing engineering work
yeah if they if they get selected
so
so the answer in brief is that israel
does not really hire astrophysicists and
astronomers isro hires engineers
aeronautical engineers and a rocket if
you have
a background in rocket design propulsion
satellite design remote sensing all
those things it's all about engineering
it's not about pure science astrophysics
and astronomy is essentially pure
science right
so uh so that's the answer the scope of
these fields in the upcoming decades in
india well india doesn't have a great
academic system india has a very
i know i know it it hurts the feelings
of people but in the indian academic
system is absolute trash it's garbage
it's one of the worst in the world
uh
the indian mind is one of the best in
the world
indians are the most intelligent people
in the world but the indian academic
system is one of the one of the worst
systems in the world there is very
little research that happened in india
very little research
so uh unless the academic system is
overhauled and reformed there is not a
great amount of scope for these fields
in the upcoming years in india
i am still optimistic that in the next
five ten years there will be reforms in
the academic system uh
especially in science it will all be
researched to be research based
but as of today it's not the case your
professors and all they don't do any
research if they do research it's just
nominal research it's not any real
research maybe one percent or two
percent of the
academicians professors etc would be
world-class the others are just
out there for the job that's all they do
so
if you want to be a world-class
astrophysicist or astronomer you will
have to leave this country at least for
some time that's just the sad reality of
of the way it is in india
so if you want to do world-class
research
in these fields
astrophysics physics
uh cosmology astronomy you may have to
you will have to
go to another country to a developed
nation maybe in north america maybe in
europe maybe some other place
and do it and maybe in the future if
india gets its act together then you may
be able to
come back and
do it in india but that's that's the
situation as of today there is no
other way to
to put it across
okay just pray the bible says
is there any relationship between our
daily life activities and the brain's
working mechanism is it true that
ambidextrous people can use certain
extra parts of their brain than the
non-ambidextrous ones
does it mean does being ambidextrous
give you some advantages listen if you
are ambidextrous it obviously gives you
advantages most people are right-handed
they do most things with their right
hand
uh writing
playing sport or whatever else
right-handed
some people are left-handed but a small
percentage of the human population is
either cross-dominant
or ambidextrous so in certain sports you
will see let's say let's take the
example of cricket
you have certain cricketers who do
one part of the cricketing activities
right-handed and some part left-handed
you know bowling right-handed and
batting left-handed or vice versa that
sort of thing that's called
cross-dominance
and you can train yourself to do that
but some people are just naturally
ambidextrous they can write with both
hands they can
uh
do various sporting activities with both
hands and so on so being ambidextrous
certainly gives you advantages in life
in in many spheres of life especially in
physical activities right
and
typically the brain is cross-wired
which means if you are a right-handed
person the right part part of your body
the right half of your body is
controlled by the left brain brain and
in the left part of the body the left
half of the body is controlled by the
right brain so that's typically how it
is so if you are right handed it's the
left part of the brain that's
controlling the right hand typically
that's how it is cross wiring
so if you train yourself
to become proficient with both hands
it's possible you can do it but you know
often some people who unfortunately lose
their right hand or arm they have no
option but to learn how to write left
handed and they're able to do it
so it's certainly possible to train
yourself to to become
more ambidextrous
that would mean that your your
right or or yeah your right brain
develops more the more you practice
something the more you train yourself to
do something you will see changes in the
physical parts of the brain that are
related to doing that particular a
particular activity for instance
there is a very famous a neurological
effect
it's called the sanskrit effect
various studies were done
on
sanskrit scholars sanskrit pandits who
would memorize massive
amounts of sanskrit literature with
mantras texts vedic texts know all that
and they would memorize these verses
very precisely even the pronunciation
has to be spot on
so
you know in the past you would have
these scholars vedic scholars would
memorize the entire vedas and all that
and it's been observed that people who
do this
sanskrit scholars
certain portions of their brains
are
developed much more
than the brains of ordinary people uh
we're not sure if it is
something to do with the language the
specific language or if you
or if you would have the same effect by
memorizing something else in some other
language but this is called the sanskrit
effect
you you speak sanskrit you memorize
since your brain develops in a certain
in a certain way and it seems
thus far so far with the evidence that
we have that it it seems to be specific
to sanskrit only so we don't know why it
is so
but what i'm trying to say
by giving this example is that by
training yourself to do certain
activities you're going to affect the
way your brain
grows and you can grow certain parts of
the brain more than an average person so
there is certainly
some kind of relationship between our
daily activities
and
the brain's mechanism for sure
right
okay uh sarikriti says
two questions
scary dream all right
firstly how are dreams generated
in dreams how is it possible to see and
interact with people i've never met
before spiritually i got an answer but
we don't want to know the science behind
it
well i'm glad you got a spiritual answer
because well okay
number two where is the mind located in
our body
most of the people most of the time
people
use i don't mind my mind is disturbed
and so on
that sort of language so what is the
mind
so where is the mind located in the body
uh
as far as we know the mind is located in
the brain
we know that people who suffer brain
damage they are mentally impaired we
know that the mind doesn't work the way
it should or people who suffer
catastrophic brain damage
they if they don't die they go into a
vegetarian vegetative state in which the
mind absent
it's just
it's just a physical body but there's no
consciousness left so it is pretty clear
that the seat of consciousness the seed
of the mind
is in the brain in the head
and that's our perspective right because
we see everything from here up here we
don't have we don't identify ourselves
with our hands or legs or whatever
this is what we identify with ourselves
with the most so
as far as we know the mind is located in
the head in the brain that seems to be
the physical seat
of this thing called the mind right the
other question is
how are dreams generated well
we don't know
you see there's so much science doesn't
know and i i see people saying that
you say all the time i don't know we
don't know well that is the truth i'm
not going to lie to you i don't know
things
no one knows these things how are dreams
generated we don't quite know how they
are generated people have done
experimentation
experiment experiments with people who
are sleeping and their brain patterns
are
the brain waves are measured and
quantified and traced and stored
recorded their brain activities is
recorded using various
instruments maybe ct scans or very
various other things
and
the brain clearly is active even when
you're sleeping the the activity is
different
the uh the waves that are generated are
of different kinds
so
so it seems that one of the explanations
could be
that when you sleep
all the memories that you have created
during the daytime they are reorganized
and they're they're physically stored in
various different parts of the brain and
that could be the reason why we need
sleep so all human beings need i believe
on average around eight hours of sleep
and sleep is very important people who
are sleep deprived they don't uh
function properly cognitively their
thinking is muddled their their
reactions are bad
so sleep is very important and it's it's
known that if you don't sleep for a
certain number of days maybe eight nine
ten days you may even die you you will
die if you don't sleep that long
so sleep is integral to your good health
and
lack of sleep over an extended period of
time is actually fatal
so what happens during sleep we know
that brain that dreams happen when we
sleep and sometimes we remember some
some parts of these dreams most of these
dreams we forget
and why do we forget that that's also a
good question
so we don't quite have the answers but
one of the experiment possible
explanations is that when we are awake
we experience things we experience life
all of that information data is stored
in the brain in the form of memories
and when we sleep the memories are
reorganized and maybe certain
connections which are strong enough are
kept and certain connections are kind of
slowly discarded and this entire process
happens when you sleep and there is the
cerebral
cerebral spinal fluid that kind of
cleanses the brain
and
prevents
the formation of amyloid flakes and all
that which could eventually give rise to
dementia and alzheimer's disease and
things like that so uh that's why sleep
is important but we don't quite have the
exact answers
as to what
is the cause of dreams why are they
generated why do we meet people
whom we have never met in real life why
do we experience certain events in
dreams
why do certain dreams occur over and
over again in some p in some cases some
people have the same dream over and over
again again what does it mean why is it
that way we don't have the answers
neuroscience is very imperfect
uh phys
psychology psychiatry are very very
imperfect
disciplines i would not even call them
science it's a lot of hand waving some
people get upset when i say that well
deal with it that's just how it is uh so
yeah we don't have the exact answers but
it's something that is
very actively being investigated and
researched
uh
many many mysteries in this field what
is the
what is the mind what is consciousness
you know and all that we don't quite
have the answer yeah so that's where we
are
okay next question
swapnil says many people think that
hydrogen can be the best form of
alternative energy okay
so the question is
where did hydrogen come from how
abundant is it and how did hydrogen and
helium give rise to so many new elements
aren't all the elements after hydrogen
and helium essentially just new
compounds
okay
so
where does hydrogen come from hydrogen
is the simplest element
one proton with an electron
around it that's all it is the nucleus
is just a single proton and there is one
electron that orbits orbits the
nucleus in
shells right so that is the simplest uh
element
in the world it is also the most
abundant element in the world how
abundant is it i think hydrogen if you
look at the entire universe hydrogen
most likely
constitutes
around 75 percent
three-fourths
of all
normal or visible matter
so all the normal or visible matter is
about four percent of the mass energy
composition of the universe
all the stars all the galaxies
everything we see in the night sky all
the light
that is the visible matter
of all of that
about 75 is hydrogen right
so that is how abundant it is
uh helium is the second most abundant
element in the world helium
has an atomic number of two it has two
protons
in the nucleus and i believe helium
constitutes about between 20 and 23 24
of all
visible or normal matter right all
baryonic matter
so hydrogen and helium are the two most
abundant elements in the world
uh
how
what are the other questions
how did
hydrogen and helium give rise to so many
new elements because of nuclear fusion
in stars
so look at the sun the sun is about 70
73 74
hydrogen and about 20 for 25 helium and
the rest is just trace amounts of
heavier elements like oxygen carbon and
so on so the sun is a massive massive
fusion reactor it is fusing hydrogen
into helium
later on helium will be fused into
heavier elements
when
the hydrogen when the sun runs out of
hydrogen
uh
oxygen carbon nitrogen and so on so neon
etc
and in more massive stars the process
goes on and heavier and heavier elements
are formed so it is all because of the
fusion reaction which is because of the
massive
uh gravitational
crushing force of this enormous amount
of
nuclear fuel
so all of these elements are created by
nuclear fusion reactions carbon silicon
iron iron is what
eventually causes the death of a star in
a variety of ways
so that's how it happens so all the
elements that we
experience
in our daily lives everything that's in
here
everything in our bodies everything on
our planet it all came out of fusion
reactor reactions
at the course at the heart of stars
we are actually made out of star
material
the
blood in my body contains hemoglobin
which contains iron
iron is produced at the end stage of a
fusion reaction just before a star goes
supernova
yeah the fusion reaction that produces
iron
consumes more energy than it gives that
it gives off and that's what causes the
eventual core collapse supernova in in
well that's one one of the ways in which
supernova can occur so all of these
elements
are the products of fusion reactions in
the hearts of stars so the solar system
was born out of
a
nebula
a big massive dust a gas cloud
which was
generated
from the death of a star
so the sun is the reincarnation of an
older star and that older star was most
likely the reincarnation of an even
older star
the sun is most likely a third or fourth
generation star
and all this material that we have on
the planet in our solar system
was created
inside ancient stars that no longer
exist that died a long time ago
so that is
the story in brief of how all of these
elements were created
next question
karan says what's a catalyst cataclysmic
variable star
uh yeah that's an interesting question a
cataclysmic variable starting is a
binary system a binary system with two
stars
so in a cataclysmic variable star you
have a regular large star
and its partner
in the
gravitational dance
is a white dwarf star so what's a white
dwarf
a white dwarf is a star that has
essentially died the sun
is going to eventually become a white
dwarf when it loses its outer layers and
at the end process at the end stage all
that's left in the core of the sun
is this massive
ball of incredibly hot carbon
crystalline carbon
so white dwarfs are essentially
spherical
diamonds massive diamonds that are
incredibly hot right
so that's what a white dwarf is
so in a cataclysmic variable star you
have two objects one let me put it on
the screen in case we have we have a
representation of that just give me a
second
cataclysmic variable star
do we have yeah there we go let me put
that on the screen so that you get a
visual representation
of what i'm talking about
so it's a binary system as you can see
there's a white dwarf
and there is a donor star
and what happens is that these two stars
in this variable
are
very close to each other
and what that does
is that
the white dwarf star starts sucking in
material
from its companion star and this
material that's falling into the white
dwarf forms an up accretion disk
and
what happens is that this accretion disk
uh
causes
so what is in this accretion disk it's
mostly hydrogen hydrogen fuel so you
have a white dwarf that's sucking in
hydrogen it's a very hot white dwarf
this hydrogen fuel is coming
is is
is being added to the white dwarf
so it's it's gaining an outer layer of
hydrogen
and once there is sufficient hydrogen
and
what happens is that the thermonuclear
reaction starts again
so the white dwarf which was quite
suddenly becomes an active star and
there's a thermonuclear fusion reaction
that starts again
which goes on for some time
and that's what causes this phenomenon
called anova so if you're sitting
over here on earth you're observing uh
this this variable star you see a sudden
increase in brightness that goes on for
some time until that hydrogen fuel is
used up and the fusion reaction stops
then again the process resumes after
some time maybe 10 years maybe 50 years
maybe maybe 80 years there is another
outburst another flare-up in which there
is sufficient fuel that is now present
on the on the white dwarf and a new
cycle starts of this fusion reaction so
it again flares up in brightness and
once again you see this star uh going
nova
eventually what happens
is that
the chandra shekhar limit is crossed
what is the chandra sugar limit
the chandra shekhar limit is the maximum
mass
that a white dwarf can have
which is about 1.44
solar masses
so as you know you have these two stars
the white dwarf is sucking in material
from its companion star its mass is
increasing every few few decades there
is sufficient hydrogen fuel to ignite a
fusion reaction which causes the the
brightness to increase
and slowly over time the mass
of the white dwarf rises it increases
and once it exceeds the chandrasekhar
limit it goes boom
supernova
and it destroys its companion star as
well
so that is the process that is what we
call a cataclysmic variable star
all right
very interesting astronomical
astrophysical phenomenon
okay crazy brain says that i i came
across somewhere that the speed of light
from a source to a surface was assumed
to be the same as the speed of light
reflected back from the surface
while its measurement and sees the
average velocity of light in both
directions
what is the possibility that the speed
of light is different in
is different in different directions
the possibility that the speed of light
is different in different directions is
zero
so
the speed of light is not always 300 000
kilometers
per second
the speed of light in vacuum is roughly
300 000 kilometers per second and that's
that's the same as in air in air
but in different media the speed of
light is slower for example in water
the speed of light is less than 300 000
kilometers per second i think it's about
2.25 times 10 raised to
uh meters per second the refractive
index in water is higher in air it is
one in in water it's one point three
three i think in glass it's even less
the speed of light it's around two times
10 raised to eight meters per second and
the refractive index in glass is i
believe 1.5
in diamond
the speed of light is about 1.25
times 10 raised to 8 meters per second
and the refractive index is much higher
in diamond so it depends on the medium
the speed of light is different in each
medium in vacuum in air it's the same 3
times 10 raised to 8 meters per second
in water in glass in diamond it's
lower the speed of light is lower but in
the same medium
light has the same speed in every single
direction
so it is not a directional thing it
depends on the medium
so that is in short the answer the
velocity of light the speed of light is
the same in all directions in the same
medium but if you have
a surface
if you have
if you have a boundary
between one medium another in that case
you will see
that refraction takes place
and light bends like light seems to bend
and the speed of light is different
in different directions
okay vish says i
i kind of know what entropy is
and its definition
but our textbooks don't explain that in
detail can you specify about entropy's
properties and its characteristics
ah my old friend entropy
so what is entropy see listen it's it's
not really possible to explain in detail
what entropy is without going into the
thermal dynamics the the statistical
mechanics the equations s equals k l n
omega and so on i'm not going to do that
because everybody
most people want get
one won't understand that what is
entropy let me explain conceptually
entropy is the measure of the disorder
of a system
of a thermodynamic system entropy is a
statistical
measure it's a statistical thing
so let's say you have a gas
you have a gas let's say you have a gas
in a box
right it has a number of molecules
a very large number of molecules
so that
gas in a box
will have a certain amount of disorder
which depends on the temperature yeah
and that's how we calculate the entropy
black holes
have entropy
black holes are thermodynamic systems so
the
this thing called entropy is the measure
of the disorder of a system and it's a
thermodynamic property of a system it's
a statistical property of a system a
single particle for instance
cannot have an entropy if somebody tells
you that a single particle is an entropy
that person doesn't know what he or she
is talking about all right so
entropy typically is something that you
find in thermodynamic systems ensembles
even a gas of photons has entropy you
can there is a certain
derivation that you can do using quantum
mechanics and and all that to
to determine what is the entropy of a
gas
of photons and so on
so it's the measure of disorder even
information has entropy in
information theory and all that
so
that is the best i can tell you
conceptually i will not go into
equations in which case i will start of
a whole a whole lecture on
thermodynamics i don't want to do do
that entropy is the measure of the
disorder of a system so a system that
has less disorder has lower entropy the
human brain
is one of the lowest entropies of any
system in the world in the known
universe
it is the most complex
system that we know of
and most likely it has the lowest
entropy that we can think of of any
system that in the known universe
the sun has high entropy but it is still
a well organized system
so it would have a certain amount of
entropy and typically the entropy of a
thermodynamic system overall increases
or stays the same it doesn't
decrease
so that overall is what entropy is i
will not go into further detail than
that for for that i would need equations
and that would not be intelligible to
99.9 of the audience
alpha beta says why do all living things
want to live
from small bacteria
to big giant animals like elephants even
dinosaurs i'm sure
everybody wanted the same thing
it's like life is programmed in that way
every living thing wants to live in
every living thing
fears death so that's what you're saying
so why are all living beings programmed
to want to live and to avoid situations
that would cause them to perish why is
that so
that's a good question
uh the primary purpose
okay let's go down to the micros
microscopic level unicellular organisms
multicellular organisms what is their
purpose in life
the purpose of these organisms is to
reproduce
the purpose of all these organisms is
reproduction that is the only purpose
they have they obviously look for
nutrition they look for good safe
environments
but the overall end result they want to
achieve is reproduction they want to
reproduce and produce more copies of
themselves more offspring
and what is the purpose of reproduction
it's to pass on the pass on two future
generations their genetic code the
genome the dna
the information contained in the dna so
all organisms
whether large or small
are essentially
carriers of dna
from the biological perspective
the
overall
um purpose of biological life
is to pass on dna from one generation to
another
so dna is the special molecule
that wants to survive somehow
and it has come up with all kinds of
tricks
to ensure
that it is propagated
and it survives from one generation to
another generation
into the indefinite far future
and if an organism dies
if it perishes
then it can no longer
fulfill this purpose of passing on its
its genetic material to a future
generation so that is why organisms tend
to want to avoid dying
so that they can fulfill their purpose
of reproducing as much as possible and
passing on the genetic information to
the future generations
and in in higher life forms like birds
animals mammals
dinosaurs etc
there is this conscious fear of death
and it seems to have the same purpose
that you stay alive long enough that you
can pass on your genetic code to future
generations to your offspring
and that's why
larger animals care for their offspring
and teach them how to survive so that
they can also pass on their dna which is
part of your dna to future generations
so that is why there is this instinctive
fear of death fear of dangerous
situations and this instinctive desire
to stay alive
now all animals exhibit don't have the
same
outward
signs of this for instance most animals
are afraid of heights
most human beings are afraid of heights
dogs are afraid of fights but birds are
not afraid of heights because they have
this evolutionary adaptation of flying
cats
are not afraid of heights cats will walk
nonchalantly on on the ledge of of a
building even if it is 10 and 10 stories
high why is it so
because cats
can survive falls
cats will always land on their feet and
even if a cat reaches terminal velocity
60 or so kilometers per hour
it can still survive that fall and
and live
so that's why cats
and birds that have developed the
evolutionary mechanisms that uh
that give them these advantages they are
not afraid of heights but they are also
afraid of death in a variety of ways
so the overall fundamental
purpose of life
is to
reproduce and pass on your genetic code
to future generations and one of the
ways to do that
is to avoid death and that's why
everything wants to live
that's why even human beings have this
instinctive fear of death and this great
desire to live
so that is what i can uh that's how i
how how i would explain this
alpha says is goldilocks zone and liquid
water really necessary for life to exist
on a planet life on earth is
carbon-based life on other planets maybe
could be based on other elements could
even be unknown elements they may live
in extreme temperatures what do you
think
the goldilocks zone
is this region around a star
where
water can remain liquid
so
when we take the case of our sun the
goldilocks zone extends from venus to
mars
so that is roughly the goldilocks zone
and the earth our earth our planet is
right in the middle of the golden rock
zone so on earth as we know we have
liquid oceans we have an abundance of
water of flowing water of liquid water
so that is the goldilocks zone it's that
small region
around a star where you can have liquid
water the temperatures are warm enough
for that possibility to be there
so typically
typically when scientists look for
extraterrestrial life they are
interested in seeing if
if you if you are observing a distant
star
if there are any exoplanets in the
goldilocks zone of that star
and that is supposed to be the place
where you should look for life
the thing is that that's the place where
you could have earth like life
it doesn't mean that the only kind of
life that's possible is earth like life
or carbon based life you could even have
silicon based life
um
there are other places in our solar
system for example saturn's moon titan
which
has a very thick atmosphere and very uh
lots of different kinds of hydrocarbons
over there it's a very cold place but
you could have
a different form of life there
hydrocarbon based life
on certain other planets you could have
instead of water ammonia based life even
there is a possibility
so
um
so i disagree that only water is the
basis of life
you could have different kinds of
biochemistries that are completely
independent of flowing water
you could have ammonia liquid ammonia
based life you could have liquid
hydrocarbon based life which which would
be very cold life yeah very cold
environments and life forms but it's
it's possible
but the thing we understand the best is
human i mean earth-like life and that's
why we look for
that's why we search for
exoplanets which are in the goldilocks
so-called goldilocks zones of their
respective stars but i agree with you
that you could have a whole variety of
of
possible
kinds of life you could even have life
in the atmosphere of jupiter who knows
there could be certain biochemical
biochemistry that could give rise to
life forms sentient life forms of some
kind
in the atmosphere of jupiter or saturn
you could even have who knows
life
on stars
very hot life
it's possible i mean that's why you
should read science fiction because
science fiction writers come up with all
these interesting possibilities
right
okay karthik says please talk about the
great attractor
so what is this great attractor it is
this it is
so the
earth
the solar system
exists in the milky way galaxy the milky
way galaxy
is part of this great massive super
cluster called the llano k or something
like that super cluster
which is
tens of thousands of galaxies right it's
our local super cluster so in our local
super cluster of which the milky way is
is a very small part
there is a certain region in this super
cluster which is the center of gravity
of the supercluster
and that is what we call the great
attractor now what lies there we don't
know
because when we look there we have to
look through the galactic plane the
plane of the milky way
and the plane of the milky way is
extremely bright
so whatever is on the other side we
cannot really see it
so there is something out there there is
this massive gravitational anomaly maybe
it's an enormous galaxy that's at the
heart of the supercluster maybe there's
something else we don't know what it is
but there is something out there
that is the center of gravity of the
entire super cluster of which the milky
way is a small part
we don't know what there is what is
there maybe in about 500 million years
when the earth goes to the other side of
the milky way maybe at that time we may
be able to see it
but we won't be there our descendants
hopefully
may be able to see what is the great
attractor so there are various theories
maybe it is
a massive galaxy maybe it's a clutch of
massive galaxies maybe it is a
region of
great amount of dark matter we don't
know what it is
the various theories exist but since
there is no direct
observational evidence we can only
speculate as of today
okay let's take one more question there
cannot be any session without ufos and
aliens so let's talk about this
so aryan says please throw some light on
the 1947 rosewell
mexico ufo crash conspiracy
so something happened in this place
roosevelt roosevelt new mexico
it's not mexico it's new mexico in the
u.s southern u.s so there is this town
called roosevelt
where
some kind of crash happened
and it was reported in the media that it
was a flying saucer or a ufo that had
crashed and apparently there were even
survivors
some alien
beings
a couple of them died and maybe one or
two survived and they were retrieved by
the u.s military
and taken to some research facility
apparently there is even some video of
an alien autopsy
i don't know if it's true or fake but
yeah it's alleged that this also
happened
so initially the media reported that it
was a flying saucer or a ufo that
crashed
maybe there could be some pictures of
that i'm not sure
you could look it up
but then the official version was put
across by the us military by the u.s air
force that it was a weather balloon that
crashed and the weather balloon maybe it
had its purpose was to detect cosmic
rays or whatever so there was a bunch of
scientific instruments on it
and the weather balloon had a certain
reflective surface that looked like
something alien so that's why people
mistook it for uh for a ufo or a flying
saucer but he said it's actually just a
weather balloon so that is the official
statement that was eventually put across
and that remains the official statement
until today
so we don't have evidence
of
it being a ufo
or an alien spacecraft or or anything
like that we don't have any of that um
the official version is that it was a
weather balloon so that is what it is so
people say some people say that it's a
conspiracy it's a cover-up it was
actually a ufo crash and then the us
government tried to cover it up by by
saying it was just a weather balloon
who's telling the truth who's lying we
don't know
as long as there is no genuine evidence
in the public domain we can only
speculate so that in brief is the story
of the so-called rosewell
ufo crash 1947. what really happened we
don't know
the official version is it's just uh it
was just a
weather balloon that crashed but
who knows maybe it was a ufo but do we
have evidence we don't
so all we can do is speculate and
that gets us nowhere unfortunately so
the thing is if ufos aliens you actually
do exist then we would like to see
actual evidence of that
video evidence maybe an interview a
podcast with an alien maybe joe rogan
could do it
somebody else perhaps
so as long as that doesn't happen
it's just speculation
right
okay i think that brings us to the end
of the questions for today and let us
now take a few live chat questions you
have questions for me
ask them in the live chat right now go
ahead and i will
take a few of these
and questions about science and
technology only people will give all
kinds of other questions as well that is
something that you can do for tomorrow
in tomorrow's session today please
questions about science and technology
only
and i can already see questions that are
not related to science
um
where are we
let me see if there is any interesting
question that i have not taken before
okay let's take a look at this
why does the sun and why do other
objects not fall down like balls in
space
what is up and what is down in space
in space there is no up and there is no
down see why do we have up and down on
the earth
because
the gravitational attraction that we
feel on the earth
is has a certain direction
the direction is
pointed straight towards the center of
the earth the earth is a sphere a
spherical roughly spherical object
it has a certain center a center of
gravity a physical center
and objects fall towards the center
that's why we have this sensation of up
and down
wherever everything falls that is down
and the opposite of that is up in space
there is no surface there is no gravity
there is no force of gravity and
therefore there is no up and down
objects are merely suspended
in the four dimensional fabric of
space-time
there is no up there is no doubt that's
why nothing falls anywhere
okay
i nominate abhijit chawda for an alien
interview so in in case you know any
aliens please let them know that i am up
for it
i am i will be happy to to to host an
alien i'll be happy to restart the
podcast
i've done 17 18 episodes of the abija
chaudhar podcast in which i have
conversations with people thus right now
it's kind of on a hiatus
i'll be happy to restart it if you if
you can nominate a good interesting
candidate for an interview for for for a
discussion if you know any aliens let
them know that i would be happy to host
them all right
so yeah
okay next question do we have anything
else
uh can the ton 618 hyper massive black
hole affect our galaxy or not
we certainly feel its gravitational
effects
every single gravitating body massive
object in the entire universe
we do feel its gravitational force
provided it is it is
um not more than 13.8 billion
light years away from here
yeah so we do feel it but it's it's a
very minuscule effect so it may be a
hyper massive black hole it may be the
most massive black hole that we know of
but i think it is
i'm not sure how far away it is from
here several billion light years away so
it's its overall gravitational effect
will be very small
we do
feel it i am sitting here i can feel the
gravitational force whether i realize it
or not of every single object in the
solar system in the galaxy and in the
observable universe i do feel it
what i feel is the overall gravity of
that but the individual component of
each of these objects no matter how
massive they are is very small because
they are all very very very
very
far away
okay next question do we have anything
else
um
uh
where are we where are we do we have any
interesting questions
i'm not sure if you have any interesting
okay this is
jai says what is the role of cockroaches
in the ecosystem
what will happen if one day all the
cockroaches become extinct from the
earth
see listen
every single organism
species that exists on the planet
has a certain role to play
in the ecosystem the ecosystem is like a
living organism itself
it's something that exists in
equilibrium in balance
you
remove a species if the species if a
certain species goes extinct it's going
to unbalance the ecosystem typically the
extinction of species in the in the in
the emergence of new species happens or
very long periods of time so the overall
effect is negligible but if for some
reason overnight
a species let's say the cockroaches were
to go extinct that would leave a hole in
the ecosystem it would unbalance the
ecosystem and there would you would see
certain effects so maybe cockroaches are
predators of some kind they may prey
upon smaller insects
i don't know what cockroaches eat yeah
i'm not an expert in cockroaches but
let's assume they are predators they
prey upon smaller insects
and that keeps that the the population
of these smaller insects in balance
if cockroaches were to go extinct you
could see an explosion of small insects
because they no longer have this
predated predator that feeds upon them
so that's the kind of thing that happens
so i'm not sure what is the specific
exact role of cockroaches in the
ecosystem there are different subspecies
of cockroaches
hissing cockroaches small ones big ones
i'm not really sure but all species all
insects all animals all beings living
beings have a certain role to play in
the ecosystem the ecosystem exists in
balance
and that's how it
is okay let us take one more question
let us not end with cockroaches
um
shambhavi says use red hit okay yeah
yeah
red hit is a spray thing right anti
anti bug spray kills cockroaches
yeah sure not a good not a bad idea
does gravity work in a different way for
microorganisms like viruses so as far as
we know
uh gravity has been tested on small
scales
and it seems to work just the way it
works at large scales up to a certain
limit
gravity we know it breaks down
the way we understand gravity
that breaks down at the quantum scale
the quantum scale is the hyper
microscopic scale the the sub atomic and
sub atomic scale
at the
scale of things like viruses
i suppose gravity could still work the
way it works
i'm sure other forces would would
overwhelm the force of gravity maybe
elect the electrostatic force and other
forces would would kind of
overwhelm the gravitational attraction
that my viruses viruses would typically
face
but i think that even at the scale of
viruses
gravity as we understand it
would still work the same it's only at
the quantum scale that gravity no longer
makes sense and we don't know how it
works
all right
anything else
why did leonardo the winches sleep only
two three hours i'm not sure if we did i
think it would be
incredible if somebody
would be able to do that
i don't think it's healthy i don't know
if it's the truth
there is a certain
category of people a very rare kind of
person
they are called
what are they called super sleepers or
or something like that
there are some people a very small
percentage of human beings who can
do very well by sli
with very less sleep
so some
world leaders have have had this
characteristic
i hear that margaret thatcher the former
prime prime minister of the uk
was able to perform very well on four
hours of sleep she would sleep just four
hours and then wake up and go back to
work
and i hear that even our prime minister
mr modi is able to function very well on
on four hours or so of sleep some people
have this thing they're called elite
sleepers
so if the story if what you were saying
about this davinci is true then maybe he
was an elite sleeper
well uh
so some people have that maybe it's a
genetic thing but most people need at
least seven to eight hours of sleep
that's just how it is on average
okay my dear friends this brings us to
the end of today's session
as always very interesting questions
keep the questions coming and i will see
you in the next episode which is
tomorrow and tomorrow we will discuss
other topics
geopolitics history and current affairs
thank you very much for all the
questions always great fun
interacting with you all
and i will see you in the next episode
thank you very much take care bye